{"tossups": [{"question": "One of these people served under Felix Dzerzhinsky before becoming a defendant at the Trial of the Twenty-One. Another one of these people proposed the Katyn Massacre. Another one of these people names a period of political repression he presided over and is nicknamed \u201cThe Vanishing Commissar\u201dafter he was airbrushed out of official pictures. Genrikh Yagoda, Lavrenty Beria, and Nikolai Yezhov all served in, for ten points, what position, the head of Soviet intelligence under Stalin?", "answer": "<b> head of the NKVD</b> (accept<b> People\u2019s Commissar for Internal Affairs</b>, accept equivalents for \u201chead\u201d, do not accept or prompt on \u201chead of the KGB\u201d or \u201chead of the Cheka\u201d or \u201chead of the GPU\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Charles Floyd was the only member of this group to die, likely the result of a ruptured appendix. The path of this group was traced due to leftover mercury in the soil, a side effect of mercury-based, high-powered laxatives called \u201cDr. Rush\u2019s Bilious Pills.\u201d Jean Baptiste Charbonneau was born into this group, the son of a French-Canadian prisoner and a Shoshone woman. Sacajawea was a member of, for ten points, what group tasked by Thomas Jefferson with exploring the newly purchased Louisiana Territory?", "answer": "<b> Lewis and Clark</b> Expedition (accept<b> Corps of Discovery</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A strike of workers gathering this resource in Anzin inspired Zola\u2019s novel Germinal. The first railroads in Continental Europe transported this resource from Saint-Etienne. Iron production was greatly increased by substituting wood with a processed form of this resource. The \u201csea\u201d form of this resource was used in locomotives and is graded between this resource\u2019s anthracite and bituminous forms. Coke is a form of, for ten points, what carbon-based rock which fueled the Industrial Revolution?", "answer": "<b> coal</b> (prompt on lignite, prompt on anthracite, bitumen, or coke before mention)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A holder of this posistion called the U.S. \u201cmore a<em> Tale of Two Cities</em> than a shining city on a hill\u201d as the keynote speaker at the 1984 DNC. Another holder of this position defeated Carl Paladino in 2010 and established the Excelsior scholarship for his state\u2019s public universities. That holder of this non-municipal position called Jeff Bezos to attempt to salvage a deal that would create an Amazon HQ2 in Long Island City. For ten points, name this gubernatorial position held by Mario and Andrew Cuomo.", "answer": "<b> governor</b> of<b> New York</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The leader of one side in this battle rejected Alfred Terry\u2019s offer of gattling guns, preferring to stay a mobile force. During this battle, William W. Cooke sent a \u201clast message\u201d begging Frederick Benteen to quickly \u201cBring Packs.\u201d Myles Keogh\u2019s horse, Comanche, was one of the only surviving members of the US military at the end of this battle. For ten points, name this 1876 battle of the Great Sioux War, the last stand of the 7th Calvary under George Custer.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Little Bighorn</b> (accept Battle of the<b> Greasy Grass</b>; accept<b> Custer\u2019s Last Stand </b>before \u201clast\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Lu Haodong was executed for leading an insurgency in this city, the first of a series of uprisings prior to the Xinhai Revolution. This city\u2019s Thirteen Factories became integral to a trade monopoly run by the <em>cohong</em> guilds, which served this city\u2019s namesake system. Lin Zexu\u2019s attempt to destroy the opium trade in this city prompted Britain to send an expedition to nearby Hong Kong. The First Opium War was sparked in, for ten points, what coastal city that names a major Chinese dialect?", "answer": "<b> Canton</b> (or<b> Guangzhou</b>, do not accept or prompt on \u201cGuangdong\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This speech begins by asking the listener to \u201cavoid the impulse to live only for today.\u201d The deliverer of this speech defended his increased funding of scientific research but warned that public policy could become captive to a \u201cscientific-technological elite.\u201d This speech notes that, at one time, plowshares could be relied on to make swords, but that this is no longer the case. For ten points, name this final speech by the 34th President of the United States which warned against the rise of the military-industrial complex.", "answer": "<b> Eisenhower\u2019s farewell</b> address", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Lynn Hunt argued that these concepts grew out of a shift in mentality influenced by reading popular novels. John Locke argued the divinity of humans as God\u2019s creations formed the basis for the natural kind of these concepts. One work named for these concepts argued that these concepts could never be revoked by government, which was instead supposed to protect them, and was written by Thomas Paine. A 1948 UN Declaration tried to formulate, for ten points, what basic universal freedoms?", "answer": "Human<b> rights</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In 2007, this man\u2019s representatives at 19 Entertainment cherry-picked numbers to announce a supposed $250 million contract. This man, who donated his entire salary at Paris Saint-Germain to charity in 2013, received the OBE in 2003 from Queen Elizabeth II. This partial owner of the upcoming MLS team Inter Miami CF is married to Victoria Adams, a former Spice Girl. This man\u2019s move to the LA Galaxy spurred American interest in soccer. For ten points, name this English midfielder, well known for his ability to \u201cbend\u201d kicks.", "answer": "David<b> Beckham</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, Ed Jackson offered governor Warren McCray a $10,000 bribe to corrupt public offices. Madge Oberholtzer was kidnapped from a train station in this state and ultimately murdered by D.C. Stephenson. A gangster imprisoned in this state used a fake gun to escape from the Crown Point jail. This state\u2019s city of Evansville was the birth place of its own branch of the Ku Klux Klan. Illinois borders, for ten points, what state where John Dillinger robbed a bank in East Chicago?", "answer": "<b> Indiana</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 2014, Thomas Hales\u2019 team finished their work proving a conjecture named for this man. English astronomer and explorer Thomas Harriot corresponded with this man about optics and cannonball stacking, the latter of which inspired this man\u2019s namesake conjecture about sphere packing. Albrecht von Wallenstein was advised astrologically by this man, whose works like<em> Harmonices Mundi</em> and<em> Astronomia</em> <em>Nova</em> were influenced by his work for Tycho Brahe. For ten points, name this German mathematician and astronomer who developed the three laws of planetary motion.", "answer": "Johannes<b> Kepler</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {"question": "This monarch was forced to dismiss one mistress when she was blamed for a life-threatening illness while he was visiting troops in Metz. That woman, the Duchess of Chateauroux, was one of four Mailly sisters who were mistresses to this monarch, who appointed the Duc de Choiseul as prime minister due to the influence of his most famous mistress. A former courtesan, Madame du Barry, was the scandalous last mistress of, for ten points, what French monarch, who also loved Madame de Pompadour?", "answer": "<b> Louis XV</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician was inspired by the Quakers to appoint Ely S. Parker as his Commissioner for Indian Affairs. Benjamin Bristow resigned as Secretary of the Treasury after a conflict with this man\u2019s personal secretary. The concept of international arbitration was developed by this man\u2019s Secretary of State, Hamilton Fish, who dealt with the<em> Virginius</em> affair. For ten points, name this 18th President of the United States, a decorated Union general.", "answer": "Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Goldsmiths gave 76 paintings as annual offerings to this building, its Great Mays. The twelve apostles are placed in a circle around Christ at the center of this building\u2019s 84-panel</b> <b>western (+)</b> <b>rose window, which was created by this building\u2019s first architect, Jehan de</b> <b>Chelles. A statue of Saint Thomas on this building\u2019s spire bore resemblance to this building\u2019s renovator, Eug`ene (*) </b> Viollet-le-Duc, who also replaced this building\u2019s gargoyles. That spire was destroyed in a 2019 fire that also largely destroyed this building\u2019s roof. For ten points, name this cathedral in Paris.", "answer": "<b> Notre Dame</b> de Paris", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "<b>An inscription tells of how one leader of this empire had the southern ocean \u201cperfumed</b> <b>by the breezes\u201d of his skills. Xuanzang and (+)</b> <b>Faxian were both Chinese visitors in this</b> <b>empire, during which caturanga, an early form of chess, and base ten numerals were first developed. Harisena served as a minister in this empire and created the (*) </b> Allahabad Pillar. The playwright Kalidasa and astronomer Aryabhata lived in this empire which was centered at Pataliputra. For ten points, name this empire that lasted from the 3rd century to 543 in India.", "answer": "<b> Gupta</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A railway partially named for this city, (+)</b> <b>Atchison and Topeka, never actually</b> <b>reached this city, which was established by Don Pedro de Peralta. Pedro Vial pioneered a (*)</b> trail to this city which was officially established by William Becknell. Pueblo Indian pottery is sold in this city, where Pop\u00b4e led his revolt. For ten points, name this capital of New Mexico.", "answer": "<b> Santa Fe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this conflict, Robin Olds commanded Operation Bolo, which successfully lured enemy fighters away from the more vulnerable Thuds. One politician\u2019s promise that (+)</b> <b>\u201cpeace is at hand\u201d ironically prompted the launching of Linebacker II during this war, which was mockingly called the Christmas bombings. Carrier-based alpha strikes were first adopted during this conflict\u2019s (*) </b> Rolling Thunder campaign, whose high casualty rate forced the US Navy to develop its TOPGUN program. For ten points, name this conflict in which heavy bombing damaged the Ho Chi Minh Trail and the Hanoi area.", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>According to the Akal Takht, women are not allowed to sing hymns in the holiest temple of this religion. Members of this religion have a combination of sugar and water called (+)\u201camrit\u201d splashed in their eyes during the baptism ceremony. Many leaders of this religion were served by Baba Buddha. Members of this religion are required to keep the Five Ks when they are baptized into the (*)</b> Khalsa. Followers of this religion wear the \u201cpagh\u201d or \u201cdastaar\u201dto cover their \u201ckesh,\u201d or uncut hair. For ten points, name this South Asian religion founded by Guru Nanak.", "answer": "<b> Sikh</b>ism", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name these Germanic people related to the Ostrogoths.", "answer": "<b> Nazi</b> Party (accept<b> Nationalsocializtische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei</b> or<b> NSDAP</b>, accept <b>National Socialist German Worker\u2019s Party</b>) (8) <b>A law code of these people, the</b><em><b> Liber ludiciorum</b></em><b>, was promulgated by Chindasuinth</b> <b>and later expanded by Recceswinth. A ruler of these people received a fragment of the true cross after he renounced Arianism at the Third Council of (+) Toledo. Defeat to Clovis I at the Battle of Vouill\u00b4e [vwee-YAY] forced these people to leave their capital at (*) </b> Toulouse. These people inadvertently inspired St. Augustine to write<em> The City of God</em> after their ruler Alaric sacked Rome in 410. For ten points, name these Germanic people related to the Ostrogoths. ANSWER:<b> Visigoth</b>s (prompt on just \u201cGoths\u201d, do not accept or prompt on \u201cOstrogoth\u201d) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In the aftermath of these events in Dayton, the Vonderheide Act was passed in</b> <b>1913. Rapid City suffered over 3,000 casualties as a result of one of these events in</b> <b>1972. Clara Barton assisted survivors of one these events in 1889, which prompted</b> <b>a shift in American law from (+)</b> <b>fault-based liability to strict liability. The South</b> <b>Fork Fishing and Hunting club was blamed for one of these events that destroyed (*)</b> Johnstown. In 1927, heavy rain on the Mississippi caused, for ten points, what type of natural disaster which often involves rushing water?", "answer": "<b> flood</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}